Inventory of the Rev. Samuel Huntting Sayre, Jr. Papers 1874-1989
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- (1)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1989 (1)
    - Ministry and Professional Correspondence, 1915 - 1979 (1, 8)
      - K and L (1, 8, 43)
        Correspondents include Richard Kennedy, George Edwin Kidd, James Jackson Kilpatrick, Mrs. (Ellen) Stanley King, Mabel P. Knapp, Paul H. Kratzip, Russell Lamson, Mary Florence Lawson, Charles E. Levering, Little, Glenard P. Lipscomb, The Living Church and Los Angeles Dean of Pasadena Convention.
      - M (1, 8, 44)
        Correspondents include Raymond C. Mackay, Bill Major, Rev. Thomas R. Marshall, H.C. Martin, Mathew County (Virginia) Historical Society, George N. Maybe, Rickard H. McKee, Lucy Mehl, Polly Meredith, Rev. Newton Middleton, Rev. John Miles, Phil Moore, R. Walton Moore, H. A. Mosher and Gladys M. Murray.
      - M - Morris (1, 8, 45)
        Includes a group of 1901 letters concerning Miss Mary C. Morris and a letter from Grandmother Morris. Correspondents include Grandmother Morris, Clara L. Morris - Cousin of Samuel H. Sayre who lives in Australia in 1957, Aunt Minnie Morris (Mary Cox Morris), Aunt Caroline Morris and Dwight B. Morris from Tombstone, Arizona.
      - N and O (1, 8, 46)
        Correspondents include David C. Narver, National Association of Manufacturers, Rev. Frederick W. Neve, New Age, Occidental College, Mrs. Robert W. Orrell and Edgar C. Outten who encloses an obituary of Miss Mary Sims, Postmaster at Hampton Virginia 1952.
      - P, Q and R (1, 8, 47)
        Rev. E. Moray Peoples, Jr., Pi Alpha Fraternity, Ronald Reagan, Governor of California (dated 1974 and during 1980 Presidential Campaign), Robert A. Robertson, Harold Barrett Robinson, Franklin D. Roosevelt, President of the United States (dated September 23, 1935) and Royal Arcanum.
      - S (1, 8, 48)
        Correspondents include Saint John's Church, Hampton, Virginia (signed by Francis W. Hayes, Jr.), Society of the Cincinnati, New York State, C. J. Sanford, William L. Scott, Senator of Virginia, Valerie Scudder, C. Vernon Spratley, Margaret Matoaka Sims and Stratford Hall.
      - T - Z (1, 8, 49)
        Dorothea Taft, Mrs. Charles E. Tolkien, Governor and Mrs. George C. Wallace, Governor of Alabama, Mrs. R. E. White, George Wickersham and Bishop S. Walters (note in letter from Mrs. Mordecai L. Marsh, Jr. dated April 16, 1947).
      - Empty Envelopes, 1927 (1, 8, 50)
      Subseries 9: Personal Correspondence
    - Personal Correspondence, 1912-1944 (1, 9)
      Commerce, Assistant Secretary of State about recommendation for Dr. Wilson Leon Godshall; Lewis Tepel; Don Kaufman; Rev. Charles Friend, the Pastor during Samuel H. Sayre's Father's illness and death; Frances R. Vance (Mother Vance), the mother of Edward Vance, who writes about Samuel H. Sayre's help to her son while her son was dying in the military hospital. They correspond for many years; Van (St. Clair Vannix) from Vermillion, South Dakota who wrote his nine page letter as a poem; Rev. E. B. Woodruff; Harvey from Maine, Samuel H. Sayre's roommate at Saint Stephen's College; Don, a friend from school; Winifred Vogan, Aunt of Stuart Gast; The Secretary of the President of the United States who says The President cannot meet with Samuel H. Sayre on the date mentioned; Wm. T. Christian, secretary of the Junior Brotherhood of St. Andrews; W. Floyd Reams who encloses a Supreme Council Badge from Richmond, Virginia; Lechner Family; and "In Memoriam" poems for Bishop Burleson by Mrs. Dora Claire Vannix.
      - Personal Correspondence, 1912-1944 (1, 9, 51)
- (2)
    Series 2: Family History and Documents
  - Family History and Documents, 1908-1979 (2)
    Most of this group of papers was found loose during processing except where noted. This series includes genealogy information for the Sayre, Morris, Carmalt and Renison families, plus obituaries, news articles, legal records and biographies of members of these families.
    - Book of Remembrance, undated (2, 1)
      A day by day book, published in December 1914 for the Members of the Bible Class of the St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia. Rev. Samuel H. Sayre noted family birthdays, wedding anniversaries and important events of his family.
    - Sarah Carmalt photograph, Undated (2)
    - Genealogy - Renison Family, 1928 (2, 3)
      Letter from George T. Renison of Great Britain to Revd Canon Renison concerning Renison family. August 30, 1928
    - Genealogy - Sayre Family, 1927, 1936, 1938, 1948, 1967, 1968 and 1970 (2, 4)
      Letter from George T. Renison of Great Britain to Revd Ganon Renison concerning Renison family. August 30, 1928.
      This group includes letters, charts and notes on the genealogy of the Morris Family, the Sayre Family and the Carmalt Family.
      Carbon copy of a typed letter written from Butternuts by Jacob, son of Lewis Morris, Signer of the Declaration of Independence. January 1, 1838
      Post card with a picture of the signers of the Declaration of Independence (1927)
      Genealogy of the Annie Morris Sayre branch of the Morris Family from Lewis Morris, the Signer of the Declaration of Independence (1937)
      Letter to Mrs. Annie Morris Sayre from "Descendants of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence" conferring "Complimentary Membership", dated June 17, 1937.
      Envelope, postmarked November 2, 1959, with notes to Bill Sayre probably by Samuel H. Sayre. Attached is a family history of the "Sayre Family" beginning with John Sayre born June 4, 1938 in New York City. There is also a photo of Morris Sayre from a publication dated 1948.
      Letter to William M. Sayre and others from John of Drinker, Biddle and Reath of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania regarding the attached A History of Choconut Lake Cemetery Association which began in 1827 by Caleb Carmalt. October 24, 1967.
      Carmalt Family notes on envelope dated April 15, 1968.
      Letter to Bill Sayre from Margaret Sayre about the Morris Family, particularly Annie Woolsey Morris Sayre. Christmas 1970.
      List of photographs of Morris ancestors from Margaret Sayre Ransone to Samuel H. Sayre. Undated.
    - Obituaries, 1937, 1948, 1964 and undated (2, 5)
      Mrs. George Edward Renison, Mother of Marjorie Renison Sayre, died January 22, 1964.
      Dr. Lewis Rutherfurd Morris undated.
      Mary Cox Morris (Aunt of Samuel Sayre and sister to his mother) undated.
      Annie Woolsey Morris Sayre (Mother of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre, Jr.) 1948. Includes her obituary from various newspapers which tell of her involvement in DAR.
      James W. Carmalt (Great Uncle of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre, Jr.) 1937.
    - Margaret Sayre Ransone, 1976, 1978 and 1979 (2, 6)
      Newspaper article on Margaret Ransone, sister of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre, when she became 1976 Peninsula Woman of the Year by the Junior Women's Club 1976.
      Program from the University of Chicago Alumni Association giving an Award Citation to Margaret Sayre Ransone, A.M. 1929 May 20, 1978.
      Bulletin from St. John's Church in Hampton, Virginia with note by Margaret S. Ransone. March 11, 1979.
    - Annie Woolsey Morris Sayre Estate, 1948 (2, 7)
      Final Report of Charles Read Sayre, Executor of Estate of Mrs. Annie M. Sayre, Deceased. (November 30, 1948).
    - Mrs. Annie Woolsey Morris Sayre - Life History of Annie Morris Sayre, 1943, 1948 and undated (2, 8)
      This group of letters, photographs, and obituaries were grouped by Rev. Samuel H. Sayre and were accessioned in a used manila envelope with the handwritten note: Life History of Annie Morris Sayre. This folder contains the following:
      Editorial about Mrs. Samuel H. Sayre from the July 31, 1948 Daily Press, Newport News, VA.
      Obituaries of Mrs. Annie Woolsey Morris Sayre (1948)
      Notice of funeral service for Mrs. Annie Woolsey Morris Sayre. (1948)
      Society news about where the Sayre families are going after being in Hampton (Virginia) because of the death of their Mother, Mrs. S. H. Sayre. (1948)
      Copy of a photograph of Caleb Carmalt with a separate note: "Caleb Carmalt in his own handwriting. A print copy of the only likeness he ever sat for or allowed to be taken. About the early 1840's."
      Letter from Morris Sayre to Sam Sayre, dated December 16, 1943, enclosing:
      Letter to Morris Sayre from Margaret S. Ransone about their Mother, Anna Woolsey Morris Sayre, gleaned from conversations, memories and their Mother's diary, dated November 18, 1943 and photographs of portraits of Governor Lewis Morris, 1st Lord of the Manor, Chief Justice of New York, First Governor of New Jersey; Lewis Morris, 2d Lord of the Manor, Judge of the High Court of Admiralty, General Lewis Morris; 3d Lord of the Manor, Signer of the Declaration of Independence and Mary Walton, Wife of General Lewis Morris, "The Signer".
    - Samuel Huntting Sayre, Sr., 1915 (2, 9)
      Grand Council Royal Arcanum of Virginia announcement of the death of Samuel Huntting Sayre, Sr., the thank you letter of Samuel Hunting Sayre, Sr. for the kindness of the members during his illness and copy of the Royal Arcanum Bulletin about Samuel Huntting Sayre, Sr.'s death.
    - Thomas Sayre Will (2, 10)
      Copy and transcript of the 1669 will of Thomas Sayre.
    - Eleanor Sayre Searle - Estate - Assets, 1966 and 1967 (2, 11)
      Stock information, real estate, life insurance and copy of the death record of Eleanor Sayre Searle.
    - Eleanor Sayre Searle - Estate - Legal Papers, 1937, 1938, 1952 and 1966 (2, 12)
      Material on estate of Mary E. Sayre, including her assets and will. Eleanor Sayre Searle was one of the administrators of Mary E. Sayre's will. Includes life insurance policy for Eleanor Sayre.
    - Eleanor Sayre Searle - Estate - General, 1938, 1942, 1943, 1959, 1962, 1964 -1967 (2, 13)
      Deeds, Death Record, Wills of Eleanor S. Searle and William B. Searle, Tax Information, Life Insurance, stock information, December 23, 1966 Wall Street with last market quotations before Eleanor Searle died on December 24, 1966, empty envelopes - some with notes, bank statements, power of attorney from Eleanor Sayre Searle to William Baum Searle, dated August 22, 1966 and other legal documents.
      Her lawyer was Richard C. Cotter of Mathews, Virginia.
    - William B. and Eleanor Searle, 1964 and 1965 (2, 14)
      Deed, Lawyers Title Insurance and correspondence.
- (3)
    Series 3: Photographs
  - Photographs, 1955 and undated (3)
    This series includes photographs of Rev. Sayre's family, his churches, his parishioners and friends.
    - Church Groups, undated (3, 1)
    - Churches, undated (3, 2)
    - Rev. (Charles) Dubell, undated (3)
      Rev. Charles Dubell.
    - Dupree, South Dakota, undated (3, 4)
    - Family, undated (3, 5)
    - Family - Ancestors, undated (3, 6)
    - Friends, undated (3, 7)
    - Bill and Jackie Frost, undated (3, 8)
    - David C. Narver, undated (3, 9)
      Includes Funeral Program and letter for C. Lee Narver, 1955.
    - Negatives, undated (3, 10)
    - St. Barnabas, Alab, Bontoc, undated (3, 11)
    - St. Barnabas Church, Eagle Rock, undated (3, 12)
    - St. John's Church, Bellefonte, Pennsylvania and St. Mary's Church, Williamsport, Pennsylvania, undated (3, 13)
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre, undated (3, 14)
    - Unknown, undated (3, 15)
    Series 4: Travel
  - Travel, 1948, 1954-58, undated (3)
    This series contains Rev. Sayre's bills, receipts, brochures, guidebooks, schedules, church bulletins, newspapers, cruise information and other material from his trips to Europe and across the United States.
    - Bills and Receipts, 1954 and 1958 (3, 16)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - England 1 of 4, undated (3, 17)
      Includes maps, railroad schedules, bus schedules, airline schedules, hotel pamphlets, brochures and guidebooks.
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - England 2 of 4, undated (3, 18)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - England 3 of 4, undated (3, 19)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - England 4 of 4, undated (3, 20)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - France, undated (3, 21)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - Germany, undated (3, 22)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - Scotland and Wales, undated (3, 23)
    - Brochures and Guidebooks - United States, undated (3, 24)
      Brochures about The White House, Abraham Lincoln and The Rolfe Property, plus a hotel sign, "If you smoke in bed please tell us Where to send your ashes!"
    - Church Bulletins, 1958 and undated (3, 25)
      St. Paul's Church in Toronto, St. Paul's Cathedral in London and Westminster Abbey in London, Church of the Annunciation in London, The Cathedral Church of Christ, Canterbury, 1958.
    - Cunard Cruise - Montreal to London, 1954 and 1958 (3, 26)
      Includes Cunard Line route, menus and a list of passengers on trip from Montreal to Europe, June 27th, 1958.
    - Newspaper Clippings - England, 1958 (3, 27)
      Newspaper issues and newspaper clippings published in London including the Daily Telegraph and Morning Post, Church Times, London Times, the London Observer and The Sunday Express.
    - Notes on Churches by Rev. Sayre, undated (3, 28)
    - Postcards, Slides and Packet Photographs, undated (3, 29)
      Includes a packet of etchings of places in England.
    - Publications, 1958, 1967 and 1968 (3, 30)
      The Countryman Winter 1967/68
      Historic Houses and Castles in Great Britain and Northern Ireland 1958
    - Publications - National Geographic, 1948 and 1949 (3, 31)
      April 1948 National Geographic article "Founders of Virginia".
      April 1949 National Geographic with article "The British Way".
    - Publications - Religious, 1957 and 1958 (3, 32)
      What to Look for in an Old Church by J. Hope Urwin 1957
      Twice Upon a Time by Brother Edward undated
      Anglican Life, Vol. 19, No. 3 April 1958
    - Publications - Travel Information, undated (3, 33)
    - Stationery, undated (3, 34)
      Stationery from different hotels.
- (4)
    Series 5: Personal
  - Personal, 1921-1978 and undated (4)
    These items were found loose in the collection, but focus mainly on his personal life. The folders include his address book, financial records, memorabilia and other personal items.
    - Personal - Addresses, undated (4, 1)
    - Personal - Insurance Receipts and Bank Receipts, 1927-1957 and undated (4, 2)
      Insurance Receipts for Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York. Empty envelopes from West Bank and Trust Co.
    - Personal - Memorabilia, 1956 and undated (4, 3)
      Paper signs that were put on Samuel Sayre's door when he was sick. Undated
      Cutout of a rabbit.
      Placemat of State Flowers.
      Receipt and shipping label for a group of sculptures from Switzerland. July 1956.
    - Personal - New York Phi Association of Sigma Alpha Epsilon, Inc., 1921 (4)
      Two $10 Shares dated 1921.
    - Personal - Newspaper Clippings, 1958, 1961 and undated (4, 5)
      Includes April 27, 1961 Gazette-Journal of Gloucester and Mathews Garden Week Issue.
    - Personal - Quotes, undated (4, 6)
    - Personal - Tombstone Arizona Material, 1973 to 1976, 1978 (4, 7)
      These items accessioned in a manila envelope with "Tombstone Arizona Material" written across the top and include newspapers, newspaper clippings and a menu.
      Menu from Wagon Wheel Restaurant, Tombstone, Arizona
      These articles have not been copied for preservation.
      Shades of 1881, Britain's Own Wyatt Earp Planning Visit To Haunts of Namesake, The Tombstone Epitaph, August 23, 1973
      Souvenir Edition, The Tombstone Epitaph, 1974
      Bisbee Review, April 10, 1975. Column by Don Pelon is circled.
      Helldorado Fever Strikes Old Camp, The Tombstone Epitaph, October 17, 1975. Handwritten note by (Rev. Samuel H. Sayres) "I conducted a communion service here on October"¦"
      Copper Runs Out but Mining Town Refuses to Die, byline from Bisbee, Arizona, Los Angeles Times, March 8, 1976.
      Helldorado celebration draw crowd of thousands, byline from Tombstone, from Herald-Dispatch, Sierra Vista, Arizona, October 20, 1975.
      1978 Special Helldorado Edition, The Tombstone Epitaph, October 13, 1978.
    - Personal - The Village Gossip Clippings, undated (4, 8)
    Series 6: Ministry
  - Ministry, 1903-1979 (4)
    This series includes material related to Rev. Sayre's ministry, such as church bulletins, employment information, professional organizations, information on his parishes and parishioners, news clippings and printed or published material that relate to his position as a rector.
    - Ministry - Ammidon and Company, 1948 and 1950, undated (4, 9)
      Clippings of the column by Horace L. Varian and Horace L. Varian, Jr. of Ammidon and Company from The Living Church publication.
    - Ministry - Church Bulletins (4, 10)
    - Ministry - Church Bulletins - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Preaches Sermon, 1978 (4, 11)
      St. John's Church, Richmond, Virginia March 19, 1978
      St. John's Church, Elizabeth City Parish, Hampton, Virginia March 19, 1978
    - Ministry - Church Pension Fund, 1941-1956 (4, 12)
    - Ministry - Employment Documents and Correspondence, 1917, 1919, 1930, 1938 and 1965 (4, 13)
      Includes correspondence and material concerning employment and ministerial related matters and organizations such as contracts, retirement, resignations, salaries and licenses. Correspondence concerning his ministerial work, whether personal or business, has been filed under Correspondence - Ministry Related.
      Lay Reader's License Authorization to conduct services in Norfolk Navy Yard to United States Navy seamen. December 13, 1917.
      Lay Readers License from the Diocese of New York for Samuel H. Sayre. November 7, 1919.
      To Rev. Lewis Nichols, Diocese of Harrisburg (Pennsylvania) from Rev. Samuel Sayre, St. Mary's Church Rectory in Williamsport, Pennsylvania. September 6, 1930.
      Rev. Samuel Sayre submitting resignation as Secretary of the Diocese of Harrisburg.
      Resignation as Secretary of the Diocese of Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. October, 1930.
      Employment correspondence with St. John's Church of Bellefonte, Pennsylvania. July1938.
      Letters to the Vestry of the Church of Our Saviour, Montoursville, Pennsylvania and the Vestry of St. Mary's Church in Williamsport, Pennsylvania from (Samuel H. Sayre) where he severs official relations with them. July 21, 1938.
      Vestry of Kingston Parish resolution that the Reverend Samuel Huntting Sayre will reach the canonical age of mandatory retirement in the Protestant Episcopal Church. December 18, 1965.
    - Ministry - Gutenberg Bible Print, undated (4, 14)
      Adaptation of a page from the 1455 Gutenberg Bible.
    - Ministry - Kingston Parish, Mathews, Virginia, 1964, 1971 and 1983 (4, 15)
      Picture of 1964 Confirmation Class
      1971 Treasurer's Report
      Photo of girls in capes and banners from Kingston Parish. September 1983
    - Ministry - Lambeth Conference in England, July 1958 (4, 16)
    - Ministry - Los Angeles Diocese General Church Program, 1937 (4, 17)
      List of Payments for all the churches in the Los Angeles Diocese.
    - Ministry - News Clippings, 1903, 1961, 1974, 1975 and undated. (4, 18)
      An Open Letter to Boys and Girls in view of Children's Sunday, 1903 by Fred. Stuart Kirkness,
      Convention Daily in Detroit Michigan, September 25, 1961,
      The American Legion Magazine. Article on surrender ceremonies of Japan on the USS Missouri. August 1975,
      The Episcopal Review. The main article is about the induction of Rt. Rev. Robert Claflin Rusack as the fourth Bishop of Los Angeles. February 1974.
    - Ministry - News Clippings about Samuel H. Sayre, 1925, 1954, 1961, 1978 and undated (4, 19)
      Farewell Sermon and Ordination as Deacon at St. John's in Newport News, Virginia. 1925.
      Appointment as Dean of the Pasadena Convocation of the Diocese of Los Angeles. 1954.
      Resignation from St. Barnabus' Church in Eagle Rock and new appointment to Kingston Parish, Mathews, VA. 1961.
      California Clergyman Takes Mathew Paris. 1961.
      Rev. Samuel H. Sayre is Chaplain of the Sons of the American Revolution and received a Silver Good Citizenship Medal from SAR. 1978.
      Mother's Day Sermon. undated.
      Sayre Guest at St Luke's in Richmond, Virginia for month of August. No year.
    - Ministry - Obituaries, undated (4, 20)
      Obituary of William E. Zimmer.
    - Ministry - Ordinations and other Highlights of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre's Ministry, 1915, 1925-1926 (4, 21)
      This group includes invitations, church bulletins, news clippings, church publications and telegrams.
      Elizabeth City Parish News and Bible Class Bulletin with notice that Bishop Mathews gave Samuel Sayre a Lay Readers license. December 15, 1915.
      The Weekly Letter of St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia April 19th to April 26th, 1925.
      Under Notes an announcement that Samuel Huntting Sayre will be ordained as Deacon.
      Invitation by the Bishop of South Dakota and the Rector and Vestry of Saint John's Church, Hampton, Virginia to the Ordering as Deacon of Samuel Huntting Sayre. First Sunday After Easter, 1925.
      Order of Service Bulletin of St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia, First Sunday After Easter, 1925. Ordering of Samuel Huntting Sayre as Deacon.
      Congratulatory telegrams from Katherine Maycock and C.C. Morris. April 25, 1925.
      Press Clippings about March 18, 1925 Ordination.
      St. John's Bible Class Bulletin which mentions
      Samuel Huntting Sayre Ordained as Deacon on April 19, 1925 at St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia. Photo of Rev. Sayre on front of Bulletin. May 10, 1925.
      The Weekly Letter, St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia. Under Notes, an announcement that Rev. Samuel Sayre will preach his farewell sermon to St. John's Church, Hampton. July 12th to July 19th, 1925.
      The Weekly Letter, St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia. March 14th to March 21st, 1926. Under Notes, an announcement that Rev. Samuel Huntting Sayre will be ordained to the Priesthood in St. John's Church on Thursday, March 18th.
      Formal invitation to the ordination of The Rev. Samuel Hunting Sayre, Priest on March 18, 1926.
      Order of Service Bulletin of St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia, March 18, 1926. Ordering of Samuel Huntting Sayre as Priest.
      The Weekly Letter of St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia, March 21st to March 28th, 1926. Under Notes, an announcement that Rev. Samuel Huntting Sayre will hold his first celebration of the Holy Communion at the early Service this morning.
    - Ministry - Poems, 1921, 1948, 1970 (4, 22)
      Poems from Rev. Newton Middleton of Church of the Good Shepherd in Norfolk, from The Living Church and from Rev. John Gaynor Banks of the Fellowship of St. Luke in San Diego, California.
      Poems of Life and Love by Emily Pinter Asher given to Marjorie Sayre by Emily Asher.
    - Ministry - Publications, 1942, 1944, 1945, 1951, 1952, 1968 (4, 23)
      Christian Nurture Series sheet with a list and descriptions of work books for Junior and Junior High School Pupils. Undated.
      Brochure of the Historic Saint Peter's Protestant Episcopal Church in New Kent County, Virginia. Undated.
      The Holy Catholic Church on The Doctrines of the Apostles' Creed by Theodore O. Wedel. Undated.
      Ours is the Responsibility, an address given at the National Convention of the Girls' Friendly Society at Berea, Kentucky. June 27, 1942.
      Fiftieth Anniversary of the Laying of the Foundation Stone of St. Margaret's Protestant Episcopal Church in New York. 1944.
      If I Marry a Roman Catholic by National Council of the Churches of Christ. 1945.
      Chapter DA of P.E.O. in Eagle Rock, California. 1951-52.
      Lest We Forget by Robert B. Watts. October 1968.